A Guide to the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1838-1987
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series 1: Literary Manuscripts
  - "Leaves of Grass," 1857-1871, 230 leaves, handwritten (Bowers #31). (Folders 50-51)
    - [Leaves of Grass] pages 56-81, Volume 2:
      - "Confession and Warning," pages 56-58, Volume 2: 1857-1859, 3 leaves, handwritten, 21.5 x 12 cm.
        On the verso of three light blue Williamsburgh tax blanks (21.5 x 12 cm.), in medium-black ink, with revisions in the same ink and a lighter one. Pinholes in center and top of each leaf. After undergoing substantial deletions and revisions this poem became section 13 of the cluster Leaves of Grass in 1860, with the manuscript leaves corresponding to the published version as follows: leaf 1 to numbered verse paragraphs 1 (now beginning "O bitter sprig! Confession sprig!") through 3 and 5; leaf 2 ("You felons on trial in courts,") to 4 and most of 6; and leaf 3 ("And I say I am of them—") to the rest of 6. In 1867 Whitman permanently retitled the poem You Felons on Trial in Courts and further shortened it by removing the first three verse paragraphs. The poem's final position, in 1881, was in the cluster Autumn Rivulets.
        - Page 56, Volume 2. "Confession and Warning"
        - Page 57, Volume 2. You felons on trial in courts
        - Page 58, Volume 2. And I say I am of them
        - Page 59. 1860 edition as published: Leaves of Grass #13
      - "Night on the Prairies," pages 60-62, Volume 2: 1857-1859, 3 leaves, handwritten, 20 x 13 cm.
        On three leaves of pink paper (all roughly 20 x 13 cm.), in medium-black ink, with revisions in the same ink, in black ink, and in light ink (including the title). As Bowers notes, Whitman cut off and flipped over the top section of the first leaf, gluing it to the rest of the leaf, in order to transform the original first line into the title. (The current verso of the top section still bears, undeleted, the first line "Night on the prairies[,]" along with the title Leaf.— and the number 73, originally 72). Pinholes in center and in upper-left margin of each leaf. Whitman deleted the pencil numbers 16, 17, and 18 in the lower-left corner of the leaves, substituting the numbers 1 through 3. This poem became section 15 of the cluster Leaves of Grass in 1860, with the leaves corresponding to the published lines as follows: leaf 1 to numbered verse paragraphs 1-3 and half of 4; leaf 2 ("I was thinking this globe/ enough for me...") to the second half of 4, and 5; leaf 3 ("O I see now that life/ cannot exhibit all...") to verse paragraph 6. In 1867 Whitman restored the title Night on the Prairies and revised the poem, transferring it and the two poems that follow it here to a different Leaves of Grass group. After other repositionings it achieved its current place in the cluster Whispers of Heavenly Death in 1881.
        - Page 60, Volume 2. "Night on the Prairies"
        - Page 61, Volume 2. I was thinking this globe
        - Page 62, Volume 2. O I see now that life
        - Page 63, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: Leaves of Grass #15
      - "Leaf (Sea-water, and all breathing)," pages 64-65, Volume 2: 1857-1859, 2 leaves, handwritten, 22 x 13 cm.
        On two leaves of pink paper (both roughly 22 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with no revisions in the verses. (The poem itself was originally numbered 71). Pinholes in center and upper half of left margin of both leaves. Leaf 1 corresponds to verses 1-5 in section 16 of the 1860 Leaves cluster Leaves of Grass, in which the poem was first published; leaf 2 ("Vast sluggish existences/ grazing there,...") corresponds to verses 6-11. In 1867 Whitman transferred this to a different Leaves of Grass group with the poems that would become Night on the Prairies and I Sit and Look Out. After receiving the title The World Below the Brine in the 1871 Sea-Shore Memories group of Passage to India, Bradley and Blodgett note, the final change was its transfer to the cluster Sea Drift within the main body of Leaves in 1881.
        - Page 64, Volume 2. "Leaf. (Sea-water, and all breathing)"
        - Page 65, Volume 2. Vast sluggish existences
        - Page 66, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "Leaves of Grass" #16
      - "Leaf (I sit and look out upon all)," pages 67-68, Volume 2: 1857-1859, 2 leaves, handwritten, 21.5 x 13 cm.
        On two leaves of pink paper (21.5 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with revisions in pencil and fine pen. Pinholes in center and at top of both leaves. Originally numbered 77. This became section 17 of the cluster Leaves of Grass in the 1860 Leaves, with leaf 1 corresponding to verses 1-6 and leaf 2 ("I observe a famine at sea—") to verses 7-10. In 1867 it was transferred to the same new Leaves of Grass group as Vol. 2, pp. 57 - 59 and Vol. 2, pp. 61 - 62, in the original order. In 1872 Whitman placed it in a different Leaves of Grass group under the title I Sit and Look Out, and in 1881 it took its final place in the cluster By the Roadside.
        - Page 67, Volume 2. "Leaf. (I sit and look out upon all)"
        - Page 68, Volume 2. I observe a famine at sea
        - Page 69, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "Leaves of Grass" #17.
      - "As of The Truth," Pages 70-73, Volume 2: 1857-1859, 4 leaves, handwritten, leaf 2 19.5 x 13 cm., all other leaves 21.5 x 13 cm.
        On four leaves of pink paper measuring roughly 21.5 x 13 (leaves 1 and 3-4) and 19.5 x 13 cm. (leaf 2). In medium-black ink, with extensive deletions and revisions in the same ink, a blacker ink, light ink, and pencil. The second leaf is a composite formed when Whitman deleted and cut away the original first two verses on the leaf, flipped the new small section (7 x 13 cm.) over and upside-down, pasted it to the foot of the remaining original verses (14.5 x 13 cm.), and inscribed a verse in light ink on the newly created blank space. Pinholes at top, in left margin, and in original and (in the case of the second leaf) current center of each leaf. This poem became section 18 of the cluster Leaves of Grass in the 1860 Leaves, with leaf 1 corresponding to part of numbered verse paragraph 1, leaf 2 ("Discovering to-day there is/ no lie,...") to the rest of paragraph 1 and to 2, leaf 3 ("Where has failed a perfect/ return indifferent of lies or the truth?") to paragraph 3 and part of 4, and leaf 4 ("And that the truth includes/ all,...") to the rest of paragraph 4. In 1872 the poem received the title All is Truth, and in 1881, after various repositionings, it was finally transferred to the cluster From Noon to Starry Night.
        - Page 70, Volume 2. "As of The Truth"
        - Page 71, Volume 2. Discovering today there is
        - Page 72, Volume 2. Where has failed a perfect
        - Page 73, Volume 2. And that the truth includes
        - Page 74, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "Leaves of Grass" #18
      - "As of Origins," page 75, Volume 2. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, three pasted sections of 6.5 x 13 cm., 8 x 13 cm., and 12.5 x 13 cm.
        On one composite leaf formed by the pasting together of three sections of pink paper (6.5 x 13, 8 x 13, and 12.5 x 13 cm.). The top section (consisting of the title and first verse) is inscribed in the light revising ink, and the lower two sections are in the same black ink. The bottom section contains revisions in fine pen (very black ink). As Bowers notes, pinholes towards the foot of the bottom section indicate that it was originally the top of a full leaf; the only other pinholes appear near the top of the middle section. This poem became section 19 of the cluster Leaves of Grass in the 1860 Leaves; in 1867 Whitman moved it to a different Leaves of Grass group in the Songs Before Parting annex. In 1872 it was retitled Germs and was ultimately transferred, in 1881, to the cluster By the Roadside.
      - Page 76, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "Leaves of Grass" #19
      - "Voices," pages 77-78, Volume 2: 1857-1859, 2 leaves, handwritten, 21 x 13 cm.
        On two leaves of pink paper (21 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with revisions in a fine pen (blacker ink) and the light ink. Pinholes in center and towards middle-left margin of both leaves. This became section 21 of the cluster Leaves of Grass in the 1860 edition of Leaves, with leaf 1 corresponding to the first three numbered verse paragraphs and leaf 2 ("Now I believe that all/ waits for the right voices;") to numbers 4-5. In 1867 Whitman placed it after what would eventually become All is Truth and Germs (see Vol. 2, pp. 70 - 73 and Vol. 2, p. 75) as section 3 of a Leaves of Grass group in the annex Songs Before Parting. In 1872 Whitman restored the title Voices. In 1881 he dropped the first two verses and added Voices (as verse paragraph 2) to the previously unrelated poem To Oratists to form Vocalism in the cluster Autumn Rivulets (see Vol. 2, pp. 27 - 31).
        - Page 77, Volume 2. "Voices"
        - Page 78, Volume 2. Now I believe that all
        - Page 79, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "Leaves of Grass" #21
      - "Leaf (What am I after all but a)," Page 80, Volume 2. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 21 x 13 cm.
        On one leaf of pink paper (21 x 13 cm.), with the title and first verse in black ink and the remaining section in light black ink or fine pen. Heavy revisions in the same inks, pencil, and a fine pen (very black ink). Pinholes mostly in center and upper-left margin. This became section 22 of the cluster Leaves of Grass in the 1860 edition of Leaves. In 1867 Whitman dropped the second 1860 verse and made it section 4 of a Leaves of Grass group in the annex Songs Before Parting (see Vol. 2, pp. 70-78). Whitman gave it the title What Am I After All in Passage to India (1871), and in 1881 it was finally transferred to the cluster Autumn Rivulets.
      - Page 81, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "Leaves of Grass" #22
    - Messenger Leaves, pages 82-94, Volume 2: 1857-1859, 8 leaves, handwritten.
      These poems were revised for publication, with independent titles, in the cluster Messenger Leaves in the 1860 edition of Leaves. Between 1860 and the next edition, in 1867, Whitman disbanded the cluster and transferred the poems elsewhere in the book.
      - Pages 82-83, Volume 2: "To One Shortly To Die," 1857-1859, 2 leaves, handwritten, 21 x 13 cm.
        On two leaves of pink paper (both 21 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with revisions in the same ink, in pencil, and in fine pen. Pinholes in center and at top of both leaves. Originally numbered 95. This was published under the same title, with only minor revisions, in the 1860 Messenger Leaves cluster. In 1871, Bradley and Blodgett note, Whitman made small but significant additions to the poem and transferred it to the supplement Passage to India. In 1881 it was finally moved to the cluster Whispers of Heavenly Death.
        - Page 82, Volume 2. "To One Shortly to Die"
        - Page 83, Volume 2. I absolve you from all except
        - Page 84, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "To One Shortly to Die"
      - "To Rich Givers," page 85, Volume 2. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 21 x 13 cm.
        On one leaf of pink paper (21 x 13 cm.), in black ink on recto and verso (in a finer pen), with revisions in the same inks and, on the recto, pencil and the light revising ink. A very few pinholes toward center. The interesting deleted verses on the back of the leaf represent an earlier version of the manuscript poem To the Future, unpublished until 1959 and currently housed in the Huntington Library. To Rich Givers— was originally numbered 98. In 1860 it formed part of the Messenger Leaves cluster under the same title. After being ungrouped (1867) and transferred to the cluster Songs of Parting (1872 and 1876), it finally appeared, in 1881, in the cluster By the Roadside.
      - Page 86, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "To Rich Givers"
      - "To a Pupil," page 87, Volume 2. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 21 x 12 cm.
        On one light blue Williamsburgh tax blank (21 x 12 cm.) in black ink (fine pen) with revisions in the same ink and the title in light ink. The original title, it seems, was cut away. No pinholes. This was revised somewhat and published under the same title in the Messenger Leaves cluster of the 1860 Leaves. It was ungrouped in 1867, transferred to a Leaves of Grass group within the Passage to India supplement in 1872 (also 1876), and finally moved to the cluster Autumn Rivulets within Leaves in 1881.
      - Page 88, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "To a Pupil"
      - "A Past Presidentiad, and one to come also," Pages 89-90, Volume 2: 1857-1859, 2 leaves, handwritten, 21 x 13 cm.
        On two leaves of pink paper (21 x 13 cm.), in black ink and pencil, with revisions in pencil, in the original ink, and in fine pen. Whitman wrote and deleted the date 1858 in blue pencil in the upper right corner of the first leaf, and inscribed the same date in normal pencil in the lower left corner of the second leaf. Multiple pinholes in center and left margin of both leaves. This became To The States,/ To Identify the 16th, 17th, or 18th Presidentiad in the cluster Messenger Leaves in the 1860 Leaves. Ungrouped in 1867, it was transferred in 1872 to a Leaves of Grass group within the main body of Leaves. In 1881 it was finally transferred to the cluster By the Roadside Bradley and Blodgett observe that in his 1860 Blue Book Copy edition of Leaves Whitman gave the dates of composition for the poem as "1857-8-9"; these editors also recommend comparing the poem with Whitman's pamphlet The Eighteenth Presidency!, edited by Edward F. Grier.
        - Page 89, Volume 2. "A Past Presidentiad and one to come also."
        - Page 90, Volume 2. Then I will sleep awhile
        - Page 91, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "To the States"
      - "To a Cantatrice," page 92, Volume 2. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 9 x 16 cm.
        On one section (9 x 16 cm.) of the same leaf of white ruled laid paper used for To a Historian, in the same dark-brown ink, and with another fragment of the same pencil draft of the speech or essay Slavery—the Slaveholders—/ —The Constitution—the/ true America and Ameri-/ cans, the laboring persons.— on verso (see Vol. 2, p. 25). Revisions in the same ink and in pencil. This was first titled To an artist, then To an architect; the smudged-out words "Lecture[s]/ To" appear in light ink in the upper-left corner. This was revised and published under the same title in the Messenger Leaves cluster of 1860. After being ungrouped and permanently retitled To A Certain Cantatrice in 1867, it was revised for inclusion in the cluster Songs of Insurrection in the 1872 and 1876 Leaves. In 1881 it was finally transferred to the cluster Inscriptions.
      - Page 93, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "To a Cantatrice"
      - "To You," Page 94, Volume 2. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 9 x 12.5 pasted to 20 x 13 cm.
        On one composite leaf consisting of two sections of pink paper (9 x 12.5 and 20 x 13 cm.) pasted together. Both sections in black ink (the upper section with a finer pen), with revisions in the same ink, in fine pen, and in light ink (the section numbers). Beneath the pasted-over section can be discerned a second title, also To You, with the number 91 (mended from 90). In the 1860 Leaves Whitman divided the poems again, publishing them in reverse order under the same titles at the end of the cluster Messenger Leaves. Section 1 was eventually published (1881) as one of the poems in the cluster Inscriptions, but Whitman dropped section 2 from his published poems after an 1876 appearance in the supplement Passage to India.
    - Pages 95-163, Volume 2: Ungrouped Poems, 1857-1859, 56 leaves.
      These poems were published without a group title, roughly in the following order, after the Messenger Leaves cluster in the 1860 edition of Leaves. In later editions they were transferred to different positions in the book.
      - Page 95, Volume 2: "Mannahatta," 1857-1859, 5 leaves, handwritten, 21 x 13 cm.
        On five leaves of pink paper (all 21 x 13 cm.) mounted on white paper stubs and joined into a booklet with linen tape. In black ink, with revisions in the same ink, in fine pen (blacker ink), and in light revising ink. Originally numbered 56; Whitman numbered each leaf in pencil in the lower-left corner from 1 to 5. Pinhole clusters mostly in center of each leaf. The leaves correspond to the 1860 published version as follows: leaf 1 to verses 1-4; leaf 2 ("Rich, hemmed thick all around with sailships") to verses 5-9; leaf 3 ("The down-town streets,") to verses 10-14; leaf 4 ("The mechanics of the city,") to verses 15-19; leaf 5 ("The beautiful city! The city of hurried and sparkling waters...") to verses 20-23. In the 1872 Leaves it was transferred to a Leaves of Grass group, and in 1881 took its final position in the cluster From Noon to Starry Night.
      - Page 96, Volume 2: 1860 edition as published: "To You," "Mannahatta"
      - Page 97, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "Mannahatta," continued.
      - Pages 98-117, Volume 2: "Poem of Joys," 1857-1859, 20 leaves, handwritten, 14.5 x 13 cm. to 21.5 x 13 cm.
        On eighteen leaves of pink paper and two of white wove paper, numbered in pencil by a collector (in the upper-right corners), and described individually as follows. (See Bowers 196-215 for more details.) Leaf 1 (21.5 x 13 cm.): pink paper, in black ink, with revisions in the same ink, a blacker ink (the number 36), and the light revising ink. Multiple pinholes in center and left margin. Corresponds to verse paragraphs 1- 4 in the 1860 published version. Leaves 2-3 (21.5 x 13 cm.): pink paper, in black ink, with revisions in pencil, in blacker ink, and in the light ink. Multiple pinholes in center and left margin. Whitman penciled in the numbers 56a and 56b at the top of the leaves, and also (possibly) a number 5 in the upper-left corner of leaf 2. These leaves correspond to verse paragraphs 5-8 and 9-12. Leaf 4 (21 x 13 cm.): pink paper (21.5 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with revisions in the same ink and light ink. Originally titled Contact and inscribed, as Bowers notes, as if it were the beginning of a major independent poem. The final verse was deleted with pencil strokes, but these strokes were erased. Multiple pinholes in center and at top. Corresponds to verse paragraphs 13-14 in the published version. Leaves 5-8 (all roughly 21 x 13 cm.): pink paper, in black ink, with revisions in pencil, in blacker ink, in fine pen (very black ink), and in light ink. Multiple pinholes in center and at top. Leaves 5-7 bear the deleted pencil numbers 2-4 in the lower left corner; leaf 8 bears the undeleted number 5, as well as the pencil number 2 at the top. Leaf 7 has an undeleted pencil 1 in the same position, as well as Whitman's pencil note "Fifth Month" above the word "May" in the first line. These leaves correspond to verse paragraphs 14 through 16 (verses 1-3); 16 (verse 4) through 18 (verse 1); 18 (2-5) through 19 (1-2); and 19 (3-6) through 20. Leaves 9-10: pink paper (the first 21 x 13 cm., the second cut down to 14.5 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with revisions in fine pen (very black ink), in pencil, and in light ink. The section excised from leaf 10 was pasted, as Bowers notes, to the foot of what is now leaf 12. Multiple pinholes in the (original) center and at the top of both leaves. These leaves bear the deleted pencil numbers 6 and 6 1/2 (lower left corner) and the undeleted numbers 3 and 4 (at top). They correspond to verse paragraphs 21 through 23 (verses 1-3) and 23 (verses 4-8). Leaves 11-12: white wove paper (both 20 x 15.5 cm., with a 7.5 x 13 cm. pink-paper section from leaf 10 pasted to leaf 12), in dark ink (thick pen), with revisions in the same ink, in pencil, and in light ink. Multiple pinholes in center and at top. These leaves bear the deleted pencil numbers 15 and 16 (lower left corner) and the undeleted numbers 5-6 (at top). The lines inscribed on the white pages correspond to verses 1-10 and 11-13 of verse paragraph 24; the three pink-paper verses correspond to paragraph 25. Leaves 13-14: pink paper (21 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with revisions in the same ink and fine pen. Multiple pinholes in center and at top. These leaves bear the deleted pencil numbers 7-8 (lower left corner), and leaf 13 still carries the number 7 at the top. They correspond to verse paragraphs 26-27 (verse 1) and 27 (verses 2-6). Leaves 15-20: pink paper (all roughly 21 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with revisions in the same ink, in pencil, in fine pen (very black ink), and in light ink. Multiple pinholes in center and at top. These leaves bear the deleted pencil numbers 14 and 9-13 (lower-left corner), although the number 11 on leaf 18 is undeleted. They correspond to verse paragraphs 28-29, 30-31, 32-34 (with a pencil X to the right of the last lines on this leaf [leaf 17]), 35-36, 37-39, and 40-41. Poem of Joys, which was never grouped in a Leaves cluster, became Poems of Joy in 1867, but reverted to the original title in its next two iterations (in the Passage to India supplement of 1872 and 1876). In 1881 it was finally titled A Song of Joys and left independent of any cluster.
        - Page 98, Volume 2. "Poem of Joys"
        - Page 99, Volume 2. O the engineer's joys!
        - Page 100, Volume 2. O the joy of that vast elemental
        - Page 101, Volume 2. O male and female!
        - Page 102, Volume 2. O the streets of cities!
        - Page 103, Volume 2. I laugh and work with them
        - Page 104, Volume 2. O the sweetness of the May morning
        - Page 105, Volume 2. Or another time fishing for
        - Page 106, Volume 2. O something pernicious and dread!
        - Page 107, Volume 2. To go to battle! To hear
        - Page 108, Volume 2. O the whaleman's joys! O I voyage
        - Page 109, Volume 2. Again we back off-I see him
        - Page 110, Volume 2. O the ripened joy of womanhood!
        - Page 111, Volume 2. O my soul, vibrated back to
        - Page 112, Volume 2. O the farmer's joys!
        - Page 113, Volume 2. O death!
        - Page 114, Volume 2. O to realize space!
        - Page 115, Volume 2. O to attract by more than attraction!
        - Page 116, Volume 2. O the gleesome saunter over
        - Page 117, Volume 2. O the joy of a manly selfhood
        - Page 118, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "Poem of Joys,"
        - Page 119, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "Poem of Joys," continued.
        - Page 120, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "Poem of Joys," continued.
        - Page 121, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "Poem of Joys," continued.
        - Page 122, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "Poem of Joys," continued.
      - "France, the 18th Year of These States," pages 123-127, Volume 2: 1857-1859, 5 leaves, handwritten, 21 x 13 cm. to 22.5 x 13.5 cm.